A Guide to the Gervase James Patterson Barger papers, 1924-1967
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Gervase James Patterson Barger papers, 1924-1967
Library of Virginia
25725
7 cubic feet (10 boxes and 34 oversize folders).
Gervase James Patterson Barger
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Gervase James Patterson Barger, Penney Farms, Florida
Biographical Information
Gervase James Patterson Barger was born 3 March 1882 in Muscatine, Iowa, and married Myrtle Grace King (1881-1972) on 11 August 1908. He graduated from George Washington University School of Medicine (1914), Harvard University Graduate School of Tropical Medicine (1915), and Brussels School of Tropical Medicine, Belgium (1927). Barger served as a medical missionary to the Belgian Congo from 1915 to 1931. All four of the Bargers' children were born in the Congo. Upon his return to the United States, Barger settled his family in Washington D.C. and began practicing medicine. he taught at Georgetown University's Medical School and headed the physical therapy department for Georgetown University Hospital. Barger also became interested in genealogy and produced extensive notes and genealogical tables on various branches of Bargers throughout the United States. He produced several books based on this research. He died 25 November 1966 in Penney Farms, Florida.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1924-1967, of Gervase James Patterson Barger (1882-1966) of Washington D.C. and Florida, including abstracts of wills, announcements, clippings, correspondence, epitaphs, genealogical charts and notes, maps, negatives, newsletters, obituaries, photographs, and published materials. Most of the collection consists of genealogical materials on the Barger family located in Botetourt, Montgomery, Rockbridge, and Washington Counties, Virginia, and in Arkansas, Kentucky, Idaho, Illinios, Indiana, Iowa, Maryland, New York, North Carolina, Ohio, Pennsylvania, Tennessee, Texas, Utah, and West Virginia. Collection contains source material Barger used in his genealogical works, including the Family Tree of Adam Barger (1962), Family Tree of William James Barger (1959), and Natural Bridge, Virginia, Bargers (1961).
Contents List
- Obituaries for Gervase James Patterson Barger, 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Arkansas Barger Family Tree, 1958-1959 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Arkansas Barger Family Tree, 1958-1959 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Blacksburg Barger Families, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Family Tree of William James Barger and Margaret Ann Boggs (Blacksburg Bargers), 1959 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Breckinridge County, Kentucky, Barger Family in Virginia During the Revolution (later in West Virginia and Kentucky), part I, 1960-1962 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Breckinridge County, Kentucky, Barger Famliy in Virginia During the Revolution (later in West Virginia and Kentucky), part II, 1960-1962 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Francis Barger and Mary Turner Family Chart, 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- William Barger and Sarah Ann Zeck Family Chart, 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- William Barger and Sarah Ann Zeck Family Chart, Francis Barger and Mary Turner Family Chart, 1959, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- William Preston Barger and Mary Ann Shafer Family Chart, 1961-1962 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- John Jacob Barger--Natural Bridge, Virginia, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- A comparison of 4 John Barger Families in Natural Bridge, Virginia, Area, ca. 1960 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Natural Bridge Barger Family VI, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Historical Data on Bargers of Blacksburg, Virginia, 1938-1962 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Fairly Complete Chartings of Several Barger Groups, Several Putnam Valley, New York, Groups with Related Correspondence, 1951-1958 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Newsletter, Correspondence, Charts, 1939-1957 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Limited Family Charts and Correspondence, 1941-1961 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Limited Family Circulars, Correspondence, Charts, 1957-1962 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Barger Family Newsletters, 1939-1958 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Lieutenant Colonel Thomas J. Barger Correspondence, Chart, 1957-1959 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Clippings, Announcements, Correspondence, 1941-1962 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- 9th Genealogy Research Institute Class, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- 9th Genealogy Research Institute Report, Correspondence, Charts, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Barger Genealogical Notes, no date (Box 3, Folder 3)
- List of Doctors Barger, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Photographs and Negatives of Tombstone Epitaphs, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Gravestones, Muscatine, Iowa, Barger Notes, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Photographs, clippings (photocopies), and oversize materials from box 5, 5"x8" index cards (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Photographs, clippings (photocopies), and oversize materials from box 6, 5"x8" index cards (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Photographs, clippings (photocopies), and oversize materials from box 7, 5"x8" index cards (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Photographs, clippings (photocopies), and oversize materials from box 8, 5"x8" index cards (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Photographs, clippings (photocopies), and oversize materials from box 9, 5"x8" index cards (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Scrapbook, Including Cemetery Photos--Blacksburg and Crimora, Virginia (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Scrapbook, Including Cemetery Photos--High Bridge, Piketon, Salem, Buchanan, Mt. Solon--Virginia and Ohio (Box 3, Folder 13)
- High Bridge Church and Cemetery (Box 4)
- Federal Population Censuses 1840-80: A Price List of Microfilm Copies of the Original Schedules (Box 4)
- Preliminary Inventories: Number 103 Cartographic Record of the Census (Box 4)
- Special Lists: Number 8 Population Schedules 800-1870 (Box 4)
- Local History: How to Gather It, Write It, and Publish It (Box 4)
- Genealogical Research: Methods and Sources (Box 4)
- The Barger Journal, June 1924 (Box 4)
- Notes Relating to Bargers and Allied Families, 1924-1963 (see also box 3, folders 7-11) (Box 5-9)
- Original Cemetery Photographs from Scrapbooks (see also box 3, folders 12-13) (Box 10)
- Natural Bridge Bargers Charts, 1956 (Cabinet 21, Drawer 14, Folder 1)
- Natural Bridge Bargers Charts, 1956 (Cabinet 21, Drawer 14, Folder 2)
- Natural Bridge Bargers Charts, 1956 (Cabinet 21, Drawer 14, Folder 3)
- Natural Bridge Bargers Charts and Correspondence, 1956 (Cabinet 21, Drawer 14, Folder 4)
- Natural Bridge Bargers, John Barger and Christina, 1956 (Cabinet 21, Drawer 14, Folder 5)
- Natural Bridge (Virginia) Bargers Family III, 1956 (Cabinet 21, Drawer 14, Folder 6)
- Natural Bridge (Virginia) Bargers Family III, 1956 (Cabinet 21, Drawer 14, Folder 7)
- Natural Bridge (Virginia) Bargers Family III, 1956 (Cabinet 21, Drawer 14, Folder 8)
- Natural Bridge (Virginia) Bargers Family III, 1956 (Cabinet 21, Drawer 14, Folder 9)
- Natural Bridge (Virginia) Bargers Family III, 1956 (Cabinet 21, Drawer 14, Folder 10)
- Natural Bridge (Virginia) Bargers Family III, William Handley Barger, 1956 (Cabinet 21, Drawer 14, Folder 11)
- Natural Bridge (Virginia) Bargers Family III, William Handley Barger, 1956 (Cabinet 21, Drawer 14, Folder 12)
- Natural Bridge (Virginia) Bargers Family III, James Washington Barger, 1957 (Cabinet 21, Drawer 15, Folder 13)
- Natural Bridge (Virginia) Bargers Family XI (Buena Vista), 1956-1962 (Cabinet 21, Drawer 15, Folder 14)
- Natural Bridge (Virginia) Bargers, 1958 (Cabinet 21, Drawer 15, Folder 15)
- Natural Bridge Bargers, Index to Family Charts, 1958 (Cabinet 21, Drawer 15, Folder 16)
- Natural Bridge Bargers Charts, 1961 (Cabinet 21, Drawer 15, Folder 17)
- Waynesboro (Virginia) Bargers, Barger-Koiner Marriage, 1960 (Cabinet 21, Drawer 15, Folder 18)
- Interrelations of Two Jacob Bargers Families and Cullen Family, 1957 (Cabinet 21, Drawer 15, Folder 19)
- Barger-Cullen-Heiserman Family Chart (Waynesboro, Virginia), 1957 (Cabinet 21, Drawer 15, Folder 20)
- Blacksburg (Virginia) Bargers (Abbreviated Chart), 1956 (Cabinet 21, Drawer 15, Folder 21)
- Barger-Koiner Families, 1957 (Cabinet 21, Drawer 15, Folder 22)
- 10th Frederick Barger, Child Philip Barger, 2nd Wife Barbara May Family Chart, 1958 (Cabinet 21, Drawer 15, Folder 23)
- Doloris Grace McDonald from John Barger and Christine Jane Tawney and from Catherine Barger and John Daniel Helm, 1958 (Cabinet 21, Drawer 15, Folder 24)
- Hazel Dempster-Dyson from John Barger and from Catherine Barger, also Doris McDonald from Elderly Related Line, 1958 (Cabinet 21, Drawer 15, Folder 25)
- Putnam Valley (New York) Barger Family, 1958-1962 (Cabinet 21, Drawer 15, Folder 26)
- Putnam Valley (New York) Bargers Chart, 1959 (Cabinet 21, Drawer 15, Folder 27)
- Putnam Valley (New York) Bargers for F. E. Barger, Drexel Hills, Pennsylvania, 1958-1962 (Cabinet 21, Drawer 15, Folder 28)
- Valentine Barger and Jane Milliken Family Chart (Ohio), 1957-1959 (Cabinet 21, Drawer 15, Folder 29)
- Eason-Shumate Family Charts (Ohio), 1957 (Cabinet 21, Drawer 15, Folder 30)
- John Herman Barger Family Tree (Latrobe, Pennsylvania), 1956-1958 (Cabinet 21, Drawer 15, Folder 31)
- Keyser, West Virginia, Bargers (Newspaper Owners), 1958 (Cabinet 21, Drawer 15, Folder 32)
- Linz, Austria, Barger Family, 1958 (Cabinet 21, Drawer 15, Folder 33)
- Petrolia, Pennsylvania, Bargers, 1957 (Cabinet 21, Drawer 15, Folder 34)